Guide to the Julian Chazin Papers TAM.228
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Julian Chazin Papers
1955-1989, (Bulk 1957-1962)
1957-1962
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Chazin, Julian
Chazin, Mildred
TAM.228
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Julian Chazin was called to testify before the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) in October 1957 in Buffalo, NY. He invoked his Fifth Amendment privileges when asked if he had ever been a member of the Communist Party. This led to his suspension and discharge from the Cold Strip Mill Department of the Lackawanna Plant of the Bethlehem Steel Company on the grounds that he had falsified his job application by omitting mention of his college degree, and that his HUAC testimony indicated that he was a security risk. Chazin contested his dismissal and won reinstatement in March 1958. The collection contains correspondence, legal documents and clippings relating to Chazin's dismissal from Bethlehem Steel, his appearances before HUAC, and his struggle for reinstatement. Also included is information on related cases as well as Chazin's correspondence with Representative John G. Dow (D-NY) and labor historian Philip Foner.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Julian and Mildred Chazin in 1999. The accession number associated with this gift is 1989.005.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
I, General Files, 1955-1989.
Historical/Biographical Note
Born in 1928 in New York City, Julian Chazin earned a B.S. in Social Science from City College. In an effort to support his family, he moved to Buffalo and got a job in the Cold Strip Mill Department of the Lackawanna Plant of the Bethlehem Steel Company. In October 1957, he was called to testify before the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) in Buffalo, where he invoked his Fifth Amendment privileges when asked if he had ever been a member of the Communist Party. This led first to his suspension, and later, on November 25th, his discharge from Bethlehem Steel on the grounds that he had falsified his job application by omitting mention of his college degree, and that his HUAC testimony indicated that he was a security risk. Chazin contested his dismissal through the grievance procedure of the United Steelworkers of America, Local 2604, of which he was a member. He won reinstatement in March 1958.
Chazin remained a progressive union activist, contesting anti-Communism in the USWA, and later opposing the Vietnam War.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, legal documents and clippings relating to Chazin's dismissal from Bethlehem Steel, his appearances before HUAC, and his struggle for reinstatement. Also included is information on related cases, including the Bethlehem Steel's discharge of Miroslaw Zelman, Edward A. Wolkenstein and Everett Jones in 1957, and Paul E. Ault, Joseph A. Picucci and John Szabo in 1955. Correspondence between Chazin and Representative John G. Dow (D-NY) and labor historian Philip Foner is also present in the collection.
Steel industry and trade |z United States.; Subversive activities -- United States.; Buffalo (N.Y.); Correspondence.; Legal documents.; Clippings (information artifacts); Communism -- United States.; Iron and steel workers -- Labor unions -- United States.; Iron and steel workers |z New York (State) |z Buffalo.; Dow, John G. (John Goodchild), 1905-2003; United Steelworkers of America. Local 2604 (Buffalo, N.Y.); Foner, Philip Sheldon, 1910-1994; Chazin, Mildred
- Series I: General Files, 1955-1989.
  - Arbitration: Bethlehem Steel Company and United Steelworkers of America (discharge of Paul E. Ault, Joseph A. Picucci and John Szabo), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arbitration: Republic Steel and H. Van Kleef, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chazin, Julian: Bethlehem Steel and House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) case, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chazin, Julian: Bethlehem Steel and House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) Case, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chazin, Julian: Bethlehem Steel and House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) Case, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chazin, Julian: Bethlehem Steel and House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) Case - Chronology, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Dow, John G. (D-NY), 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Foner, Philip, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miroslaw Zelman, Edward A. Wolkenstein, Everett Jones v. Bethlehem Steel Company and United Steelworkers of America, AFL-CIO(United States District Court), 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Supplemental Unemployment Benefits, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)